#大家好 現在去看一下我上次寫名字的那個拿藤果啊
Hi everyone. We're now going to have a look at the wild melon with my name written on it.
#看一下熟了沒有
Let's see if it's ready or not.
#帶了一個袋子
I have a bag with me.
#有的話就把它裝回去
We can take them back home if they are ready.
#順便要看一下還有沒有板栗
We can also see if there're still any chestnuts.
#你看 攝影小哥家的攀蒲
Look! These are the "panpu" (pumpkins) at Mr. Cameraman's place.
#又長出一個來
A new one has grown.
#這個小攀蒲很嫩的哦
This little "panpu" should be very tender.
#等一下我帶回去
Let me bring it back,
#帶回去直接炒肉
bring it back and fry with meat,
#可以
perhaps,
#炒豬肉
pork.
#不長啦
Nothing
#哇 還沒熟哦 你看
Wa! It's still not yet ready, look!
#這是我的名字
This is my name,
#還有一個 專享
and here, "exclusive enjoyment".
#好大 現在 你看
It's huge now, look!
#沒熟
Not ready yet.
#這也有幾個
Here're a few more.
#你看 現在長了好大條啦
Look! They're getting really big and long now.
#這裡
Here.
#這裡也有一個
And here is another one.
#這個
This,
#這個應該是被那個鳥吃啦
this must have been eaten by birds,
#啄 抓了兩下
pecked, scratched by birds.
#沒事
Never mind.
#沒熟
It's still green.
#這熟的[SIC]太慢啦 今年
It takes so much time this year.
#看一下有沒有板栗撿
Let's see if we can pick any chestnuts.
#你看 這有一顆[SIC]牛奶果樹哦
Look! Here is a milk fruit tree.
#一摘出來就很多那個白白的那個奶
Once it's picked, there's a lot of white juice.
#牛奶一樣的
And it looks like milk.
#我們就叫它牛奶果
So it is called "milk fruit".
甘甜甘甜的
It's savory sweet.
#都沒有幾個
There're just a few.
#嗯
Um!
#味道好極啦
Marvelous!
#一個 一個板栗都沒有
Not, not even one single chestnut.
#哇 這裡有一顆[SIC]攀蒲哦
Wa! Here's a "panpu".
#它現在 現在不摘掉也會爛掉的
Now, it would be rotten if it's left here.
#現在天冷啦
It's now getting cold.
#剛好
It's good,
#剛好我拿了一個大的袋子
it's good that I have a large bag with me,
#剛好被我看到
and the "panpu" is in front of me.
#看一下有沒有啦
Let's see if there're any.
#你看 這個那麼小也要摘掉
Look! I'll take this one even it's that small.
#不摘掉的話沒用的現在 現在都變形啦
There's no point leaving it here. It's already deformed now.
#這還有一個小的
Here's another small one.
#這種攀蒲很嫩的
This kind of "panpu" is very soft and tender.
#很好吃的哦
It tastes really good.
#這個攀蒲放在這裡哦
I'll leave the "panpu" here first.
#我們去看一下那棵板栗樹
Let's take a look at the chestnut tree.
#看有沒有
See if there're any.
這個板栗呀 掉的太快啦
The chestnuts, fell too qucikly.
#一個禮拜左右
In just a week,
#就甚麼都沒啦
nothing is left.
#啊 幸好沒有白來 有幾個攀蒲
Ah! Luckily our effort is still worthy, with the "panpu".
#帶回去
Bring them back.
#剛好這板栗樹旁樹有幾個玉米喲
There're a few corns right next to the chestnut tree.
#兄弟家種的
They're grown by my buddy.
#他現在已經摘了一遍的
He has already harvested once.
#摘了一遍 你看 那麼大的他都不要
But still, look, he left such a big one here.
#這敗家仔
What a prodigal guy!
#我帶回去賞一下 好不好吃
Let me bring it back and see, see if it tastes good.
#你看 不要(註︰但我聽到的是「哎喲」) 有蟲 怪不得他不要
Look! Ayo, a bug. That's why he didn't take it.
#沒壞吧
It's still fine.
#你看 兄弟家的玉米 那麼標亮他都不要
Look! My buddy's corn. It's so pretty but he didn't take it.
#那裡 你看 就是稍微短了一點
Why? Look! It's just a bit short,
#胖了一點而已
and a bit fat.
#它[SIC]就不要啦 (註︰這個意思稍為改了一下，一來英語沒有很貼切的短句，二來上面的「而已」較想譯出來)
Nothing serious
#太浪費啦
What a waste!
#我摘兩個回去吃一下
I'll pick a few home.
#你看 這個 那麼靚的玉米 他竟然不要
Look! How can such a beautiful corn be left here?
#我帶回去吃
I'll take it.
#我帶牛皮袋來裝
I have a bag with me.
#牛皮袋它在外面 我會去裝起來
The bag is out there. I'll carry the corns with it.
#啊 終於
Ah! Finally, we,
#到 到這個旁邊啦
ar, arrive at the bag.
#這個袋子太小啦
The bag is too small.
#裝都裝不下
It's almost filled up.
#我們看一下
Let's see.
#哎喲
Ayo!
#還能背得動
It's still alright for me.
#誒
Eh?
#這裡有這個萵笋哦
Here's a celtuce!
#有 (註︰有甚麼......)
Yeah
#你看 這個小萵笋
Look! This small celtuce,
#這個很嫩的哦 這個
it must be tender and juicy.
#一口
A bite,
#一口就可以把它悶掉 (註︰其實「悶掉」是甚麼意思？)
a single bite is enough to finish it.
#嗯
Um!
#這個可以生吃的
It can be eaten raw.
#小時候經常摘來吃 (註︰我省掉了「吃」這概念，因為譯作"get a lot to eat"好像有點生硬，但保留"eat"則不清楚是到處摘還是家裡有，但"get"應該清楚有「吃」的意思
I used to eat a lot of these when I was a kid.
#那裡有水
There's water on the ground.
#這都老啦
These are too old.
#要找嫩的
We need the younger ones.
#這裡有一個
Here's one.
#這個稍微有點老
This is a bit old.
#但是還行
but still fine.
#還可以吃得下
It's still edible.
#很好吃的哦
It's very tasty.
#下次來
Next time,
#下次穿到水鞋來
next time I'll come again in water boots.
#這不方便
It's too much trouble.
#鞋子都進水啦
The water goes into my shoes.
#有點老 不要啦
Enough, it's a bit old.
#嗯 被嗆了一下
Um, got chocked.
#這個
The,
#這個攀蒲太重啦 我找個 找個棍子來
the "pampu" are too heavy. I'll get, get a rod,
#抬回去
to carry it.
#反正有兩個人
Both of us are here.
#可以
Okay!
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#我們要回去啦
We're heading back now.